Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is ק"ט. Kuf Tet.
We pick up in the middle of ק"ח עמוד ב'. Kuf Chet
Amud Bet. We're dealing with the whole case about a מיאון Me'un
that follows a גט, Get, same man or different man, whether it
redefines the woman as a non-גרושה Grusha
for relevance of interesting the משנה Mishnah speaks about relevance of a
case of מחזיר גרושתו, Machzir Grushato, so taking her back. It doesn't
discuss relevance of a כהן, Kohen, but one imagines that would be
the same. And basically the משנה Mishnah has said that if it's
the same man and he does מיאון Me'un after גט, Get, he
remarried her, then it redefines her status. You go by the latter
status. If it was a different man, he divorced her and another
man married her and did מיאון, Me'un, it does not. Rather than
making it based on a more like I would
say the same man can redefine her status not a different man,
the גמרא Gemara makes it based on a question about whether we're
afraid that he will, the גמרא Gemara sort of takes it for
granted that he should be able to, even a different man should
be able to redefine her status, thank you, but the question is
whether that will lead to a problem, whether that will lead to
her first husband trying to essentially seduce her to do מיאון Me'un
with the second husband or not based on signaling her and so
on, and that's something that we want to prevent. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara continues with that, let's just get a little bit make
a little progress here. The גמרא Gemara continues so we pick up
in the middle of ק"ח עמוד ב'. Kuf Chet Amud Bet.
It's right, it's about a third of the way down. There's a
little ד' Dalet in parentheses. Two words in. Line starts with the
word שבשבילו She-bishvilo ולא ישתבש. Velo Yishtabesh. So the גמרא Gemara says
אלא איכא השתא בינא. Ella Ika Hashta Bina.
We get that there's a difference between a מיאון Me'un following a
גט Get with the same man or a different man, and the
משנה Mishnah is not a problem. But איכא השתא דחבריה אדחבריה קשיא.
Ika Hashta Dechavrei Adechavrei Kashya. It's still a problem in terms of
comparing when a second man does מיאון. Me'un. Where is that a
problem? The משנה Mishnah contradicts itself. קשיא. Kashya. מיאנה בו והחזירה, Mi'ena
Bo Vehichzira, because here's what the משנה Mishnah says. First it says
מיאנה בו והחזירה, Mi'ena Bo Vehichzira, she did מיאון Me'un and then
he took her back. נתן לה גט, Natan Lah Get, and then
he gave her a גט. Get. ונישאת לאחר, Venisset Leachair, and then
she married another person. ונתאלמנה או נתגרשה, Venisalman Oh Nisgarsha, and then
from guy number two he died or divorced her.
אסורה לחזור לו, Assura Lachzor Lo, she can't go back because that
would be מחזיר גרושתו. Machzir Grushato. Okay, so טעמא דנתאלמנה או נתגרשה,
Ta'ama Denisalman Oh Nisgarsha, the reason she can't go back to guy
number one is because guy number two either died or divorced her.
הא מיאנה, Ha Mi'ena, what if guy number two had what if
that had not been a death or divorce? What if she had
done מיאון Me'un with guy number two? מותרת לחזור לו, Muteret Lachzor
Lo, that sounds like that she could go back to guy number
one. אלמא אתי מיאון דחבריה ומבטל גיטא דידיה, Alma Asi Me'un Dechavrei
Umevatel Gita Didey, so even the second guy's מיאון Me'un would redefine
her status. Okay, so that's a דיוק. Diyuk. I don't know if
any of us would have made that דיוק Diyuk in the משנה.
Mishnah. Again, to me it's completely natural to say the first guy
can redefine her status not the second guy, but the גמרא Gemara
says in the case of the משנה Mishnah where first he basically
did מיאון Me'un to her. Okay, first he did מיאון, Me'un, she
did מיאון Me'un to him, thank you, she did מיאון Me'un to
him. Okay, then that was then he remarried her. Okay, and then
stage number two he gave her a גט. Get. Okay,
and then she went ahead after the גט Get and married guy
number two. Okay, so the משנה Mishnah says once if guy number
two dies or divorces her, she can't go back to guy number
one because it's מחזיר גרושתו Machzir Grushato because גט Get was the
most recent status. Okay, it's totally reasonable, right? But it says ah
it said guy number two died or died or divorced her, the
implication is if she had done מיאון Me'un to guy number two
she could go back, and that מיאון Me'un she did to guy
number two would redefine her status as a non-גרושה Grusha even vis-a-vis
guy number one. All right, so that's the דיוק Diyuk because it
speaks only here about גט Get or מיתה Mita and not about
מיאון. Me'un. The גמרא Gemara is saying we should be מדייק Medayek
that if she's מיאון Me'un with guy number two, it redefines her
status. One minute, so how does that contradict? Because the end of
the משנה Mishnah makes it clear that מיאון Me'un with a different
guy does not redefine her status. Okay, so אלמא אתי מיאון דחבריה
ומבטל גיטא דידיה, Alma Asi Me'un Dechavrei Umevatel Gita Didey, so guy
number two's מיאון Me'un undermines guy number one's גט. Get. ורמינהי, Ureminhi,
and I'll ask you on this. הממאנת באיש ונישאת לאחר וגירשה לאחר
ומיאנה בו, Ha-mema'enes Be'ish Venisset Leachair Veigirsha Leachair Umi'ena Bo, ונישאת וגירשה
ומיאנה Venessais Veigirsha Ve-mi'ena etc. you know, she marries multiple husbands alternating
between מיאון Me'un and גט, Get, right that was the. הממאנת באיש
וניסת לאחר וגירשה לאחר ומיאנה בו,
Hamema'enet beish venisat le'acher
vegerasha le'acher veme'ana bo, הממאנת באיש וניסת אחר וגירשה
אחר ומיאנה בו, Hamema'enet beish venisat acher vegerasha acher veme'ana bo, זה
הכלל, ze haklal, and then it goes
on, you know, וניסת וגירשה ומיאנה, venisat vegerasha veme'ana, etc. You know,
because she marries multiple husbands alternating between מיאון me'un and גט, get,
right? That was the scenario. And then the משנה mishnah ends by
saying זה הכלל, ze haklal, this is the rule: כל שיצאת ממנו
בגט אסורה לחזור לו. kol sheyatzat mimeno beget asura lachazor lo. Anybody
she got a גט get from she can't go back to, even
though she got a מיאון me'un from the from the husband that
followed or she did a מיאון me'un with the husband that followed.
ובמיאון uveme'un anybody she left with a מיאון me'un she can go
back to. אלמא alma so the end of the משנה mishnah is
very clear
that לא אתי מיאון דחברי ומבטל גיטא דידי.
lo ati me'un dechavre umevattel
gita didei. A מיאון me'un which she does with a different husband
does not undermine and redefine her גרושה grusha status vis-a-vis the first
husband. vis-a-vis the first husband. So how do you do it? Does
a מיאון me'un with another guy redefine her status or no? So
אמר רבי אלעזר amar Rabbi Elazar תוברא. tovra. So here is where
we're getting the problem of the משנה. mishnah. This is the real
problem about whether with the second guy it can redefine her status.
So רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar said you're right. It's a break the
משנה mishnah in half. מי ששנה זו לא שנה זו. mi sheshana
zu lo shana zu. The one who taught the first part of
the משנה mishnah didn't teach the second. The first part of the
משנה mishnah suggests a second guy's מיאון, me'un, a מיאון me'un with
a second guy can redefine her status, and the end of the
משנה mishnah says no, only a מיאון me'un with the same guy
can redefine the status, not a מיאון me'un with a different guy.
That's what he says. עולא אמר Ulla amar no. Here's why the
cases are different. כגון kegon both of these answers assume that it
was a good דיוק diyuk that the first part of the משנה
mishnah does make it sound like a מיאון me'un of another guy
will work. And here's the difference: כגון ששילשה בגיטין. kegon sheshilshe begetin.
The case of the second case when another guy's מיאון me'un doesn't
work is that there were three גיטין. getin. Okay, right? It was
a case that, the case was, right, she kept on going from
one guy to the next. So first guy she did מיאון, me'un,
second guy she got a גט, get, next guy she did a
מיאון, me'un, next guy she got a גט, get, next guy she
did מיאון, me'un, next guy גט. get. Okay, so there were three
גיטין. getin. After there were three גיטין, getin, then no מיאון me'un
will redefine because it happened three times, it makes it clear that
she's got a גרושה grusha status. Ironically, when not ironically, interestingly, only
a גרושה grusha status for the people she received a גט get
from, not like an objective גרושה grusha status to the other guy.
Okay, so it makes a very special case of the last case
of the משנה. mishnah. In principle you're right, מיאון me'un of another
guy would redefine her status. But if there were three גיטין, getin,
then
then her גרושה grusha status at least vis-a-vis the guys she got
גיטין getin from, that doesn't get changed. She can go back to
the guys she got מיאון me'un from. Okay, very strange. Okay. כגון
ששילשה בגיטין דמיחזי כגדולה. kegon sheshilshe begetin demichzi kegdola. At that stage,
it looks like she's an adult. She's got so many גיטין, getin,
nobody looks at her as a קטנה ktana anymore. And again, that
fixed her status at least vis-a-vis the guys she got גיטין getin
from. Again, very complicated. The logic, the intuitive logic is that what
she gets from another guy should never redefine her status, but the
גמרא gemara is assuming either that there's a תנא tanna out there
that what she gets from guy number two
will redefine her status from guy number one, makes her a non-גרושה
grusha even vis-a-vis guy number one, or that
at least it would do it as a regular rule unless there
was a case of three גיטין. getin. So really allowing very seriously
for the possibility that another guy's מיאון me'un redefines her status from
guy number one. Yes.
Particularly in light of שילשה בגיטין, shilshe begetin, I assume that this
whole thing could even potentially work because she's קטנה ktana throughout the
entire process.
Yes, the whole thing is that she's קטנה, ktana, right.
Because if she were גדולה gdola in the middle, the גט, get,
the מיאון me'un would never be able to...
Sure. All of this, right, the whole fact that we keep on
talking about מיאון me'un and the whole fact that a גט get
is not a גט דאורייתא get de'oraita and can redefine her status...
Right, this whole thing is דרבנן.
derabbanan. This whole thing is דרבנן. derabbanan. The גט get is דרבנן,
derabbanan, the קידושין kiddushin is דרבנן, derabbanan, everything is דרבנן. derabbanan. That's
why we're able to speak about redefining the status.
And they only agreement for the first
guy, whatever...
Sure, that's explicit in the משנה. mishnah. מאן תנא man tanna now,
if it's a debate of תנאים tanna'im according to the first answer,
who is the תנא tanna that would say that, you know, where
do we see this position in the תנאים tanna'im that another guy's
מיאון me'un does not redefine her status, or does redefine, like where
do we see this debate of the תנאים tanna'im because we're claiming
it's a debate of תנאים? tanna'im? So מאן תנא? man tanna? So
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב. amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav. מאי דכתיב?
mai dechtiv? So it's a, you know, it's funny, it doesn't quote
דתניא detanya or whatever, it just starts with the statement אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב. amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav. מאי דכתיב, mai dechtiv,
what's meant by the verse
מימינו בכסף שתינו עצינו במחיר יבואו? meimenu bechesef shatinu ateinu bimchir yavo'u?
Our water we had to drink with silver and our, you know,
our wood
we had to, our firewood presumably had to come
with purchase.
Oh, you mean we have to pay for our wood?
Yes, that's what it means, we had to pay for wood.
You say pay
with, oh, you mean I pay with silver, right, I did not
mean drink in silver cups, right. Okay, right. We had to pay
for our water and pay for our wood, right? This is of
course, you know, פסוק pasuk about איכה, Eicha, about the חורבן. churban.
What does that mean? So using the classic metaphor that water represents
תורה, Torah, בשעת הסכנה, besha'at hasakana, at the time of danger, meaning
during the, you know,
Hadrianic persecutions, נתבצרה הלכה זו, nitbatzra halacha zu, the following הלכה halacha
was asked, it was like, you know, searched out, meaning we didn't
know the answer to it. הרי שיצתה מראשון בגט ומשני במיאון. harei
sheyatzta merishon beget umisheni beme'un. Exactly this case. Guy number one gives
her a גט, get, guy number two does a מיאון. me'un. Does
מיאון me'un of guy number two redefine her status? מהו שתחזור לראשון?
mahu shetachzor lerishon? Can she go back to guy number one? Okay,
so does the מיאון me'un of guy number two redefine her status
or no? Exactly what we were saying is maybe a מחלוקת תנאים
machlokes tannaim that the two parts of our משנה mishna disagree on.
So that was the question that was asked.
שכרו אדם אחד Sachru adam echad בארבע מאות זוז. be-arba me-os zuz.
They hired a person with 400 זוז. zuz. 400 is always an
exaggeration. ושאלו את רבי עקיבא בבית האסורים. v'sha-alu es Rabi Akiva b'be-asurim.
Before we mentioned that רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva was in prison by
a חליצה chalitza case. Here we have a case where he's... or
there it wasn't so explicit. Here we have an explicit case he's
in prison. They hired a guy to go smuggle in the following
question to רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva in prison. ואסר. V'assar. And he
said it's forbidden. Maybe they had to pay the guard, they had
to bribe the guard in order that they could get through or
something. Anyway, he said ואסר. v'assar. It's אסור. assur. The מיאון miyun
of guy number two does not change her status. ושאלו את רבי
יהודה בן בתירה בנציבין. v'sha-alu es Rabi Yehuda ben Beseira b'Nitzivin. Then
they went to ask רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabi Yehuda ben Beseira
in נציבין. Nitzivin. Maybe they didn't have to bribe a guard but
they had to send somebody there. ואסר. V'assar. And he said forbidden.
Guy number two does not redefine her status. Okay. אמר רבי ישמעאל
בר רבי יוסי. Amar Rabi Yishmael bar Rabi Yose. So that was
anyway that's just an example of times of persecution where we had
to spend so much money in order not for water but in
order for תורה. Torah. אמר רבי ישמעאל בר רבי יוסי. Amar Rabi
Yishmael bar Rabi Yose. Said רבי ישמעאל בר רבי יוסי. Rabi Yishmael
bar Rabi Yose. We've seen him before also in these discussions. לזו
לא הוצרכנו. L'zu lo hutztarchnu. This wasn't a question. This is obvious
that actually against רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva that a מיאון miyun of
a second guy can redefine her status. Why? איסור כרת התרת. Issur
kares hitarta. If you allow a מיאון miyun to permit an איסור
כרת. issur kares. How does a מיאון miyun permit an איסור כרת?
issur kares? Well, a virtual איסור כרת. issur kares. She's considered married
to a guy, she does מיאון, miyun, and then she goes sleep
with another guy. So the מיאון, miyun, you know, undermines קידושין. kiddushin.
Obviously it's a rabbinic קידושין kiddushin but we give the power of
מיאון miyun to redefine her as a non-married woman. So if מיאון
miyun can redefine her as a non-married woman, it should certainly be
powerful enough to remove the problem of מחזיר גרושתו machzir grushaso to
let her go back to the husband. Okay. So of course there's
a big difference. The מיאון miyun redefines her status vis-a-vis the guy
she's doing מיאון miyun with, not vis-a-vis a different guy. But that's
what רבי ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael says. רבי ישמעאל בר רבי יוסי Rabi
Yishmael bar Rabi Yose says מיאון miyun with guy number two can
allow her to go back to guy number one. לזו לא הוצרכנו.
L'zu lo hutztarchnu. איסור כרת התרת. Issur kares hitarta. If מיאון miyun
permits her an איסור כרת, issur kares, איסור לאו לא כל שכן?
issur lav lo kolsheken? How much more so would it permit an
איסור לאו issur lav of letting her go back to guy number
one. So he says he disagrees with רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda and
רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva who say that guy number two does not
redefine her status. He says of course it does. If she does
a מיאון miyun even with guy number two, redefines her status, go
back to guy number one.
So
ברם כך שאלו. beram kach sha-alu.
So he denies that that was the question and that was the
response because he thinks it's obvious the response is that it's מותר.
muttar. Here was the question that was asked when they went to
get רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva in the prison.
It was a throwaway, so no one knows.
No, that was a good point.
הרי הייתה אשת אחי אמו שהיא שנייה לו. Harei haysa eshes achi
imo she-shniya lo. Okay, so a guy's wife... uncle's wife... now
we get to do another fun case. Not like not this case
at all. Yes, but it's his aunt because it's his mother's... it's
his mother's brother. Okay. So here's his mother's brother. Okay. Here's him.
He's maternal...
okay, here's his brother, אח.
ach. He's his brother's wife who happens to be a קטנה. ketana.
We'll get to that. Okay. That's אשת אחי אמו. eshes achi imo.
Okay, now, okay. Now he's אסור assur to her מדרבנן. mi-derabanan. His
aunt, his mother's sister or father's sister is an איסור דאורייתא. issur
de-oraisa. His mother's brother's wife is an איסור דרבנן. issur de-rabanan. Okay,
so that's the case. איסור דרבנן. issur de-rabanan.
His paternal brother. Okay. Here's his paternal brother. So
different mother. So it's a different mother, he can marry this woman,
right? Yes, because he's not related to... right. Here's... wait. Why do
I have this? Yeah, this is his mother, right, and this is
his father. So here, anyway, but this guy comes from a different
mother. Okay, so you see
they've got the same father, right? Okay. They've got the same father.
It's going to mean that יבום yibum is possible, right? This guy
goes ahead and marries his half-brother's aunt, right? Totally okay because it's
not related. It's on the mother's side. Alright, so these two get
married. Alright.
Now, of course and she's still a קטנה.
ketana. She's still a קטנה. ketana.
Of course what's going to happen?
He's going to die. Okay. Can she go ahead and
do יבום yibum to her... well, no, because it's an ערווה דרבנן.
erva de-rabanan. But you know how he could do יבום yibum to
her? If she went ahead and did מיאון, miyun, not to the
guy she was most recently married to, because guy number one must
have like left whatever, you know, it's not exactly clear what happened
here. Maybe got a גט get or something like that, or he
died or whatever. Anyway, she can go ahead and go back and
do מיאון miyun in her first wedding. So therefore she was never
an ערווה, erva, so it'll allow him to do יבום yibum now.
But you can do מיאון miyun afterwards?
Yeah, well we've had that, right? We've had the case about she,
you know, about when there's after, I mean we've
had... it's pretty ironic because here, right, because normally we'd have doing
מיאון miun when there still is זיקה zikah retaining the relationship, right?
Here there's a מיאון, miun, right,
after whatever, the guy gave her גט, get, after the guy died,
right, and retroactively she's doing
מיאון miun back on the first marriage. It's pretty funny.
Let me just understand this. The Romans are killing Jews in the
streets and Rabbi Akiva sitting in jail with a whiteboard trying to
figure this out?
That's exactly it. I think that's the beauty of this story. All
right.
So let's... in order to discover...
oh no, so he would anyway do חליצה. chalitzah. She'd do מיאון
miun so that he could do יבום. yibum.
Like he has to be מבטל mivatel a status so he can...
you're not getting it? She was married to his brother, okay? So
then she was never an עריות. arayot. She's not doing מיאון miun
to him, right? She's doing מיאון miun to her first marriage to
this guy which made her an עריות arayot to him.
Oh, okay. Okay, but it's very bizarre because she's already obviously no
longer married to this guy because he died or divorced her or
whatever, right? She's married to him, there's no, it's not like there's
a זיקה zikah that she's doing מיאון miun to. She's just going
back, oh, five years ago that guy was married to who then
died on me or whatever, I'm doing מיאון miun on him. She's
still a קטנה, ktana, right. So that's the question. Okay, okay,
where were we?
So,
is this the same thing as a
יבום דרבנן yibum derabbanan in this case?
No...
well yes, yes, that is a יבום דרבנן, yibum derabbanan, would that
these cases of קטנה ktana would be a case... that's what we've
been dealing with since the beginning of the פרק, perek, exactly. Okay.
הרי היתה אשת אחיו עמו שהיא שניה לו, Harei hayta eshet achiv
imo shehi shniya lo, it's an איסור עריות דרבנן, issur arayot derabbanan,
that's what שניה shniya means. ונשא אחיו מאביו, Venasa achiv me'aviv, his
paternal brother married her. ומת, Umeyt, and then he died. מהו שתמאן,
Mahu shetema'en, can she do מיאון miun with the first guy? השתא,
Hashta, now doing מיאון miun even though now she's already on dead
husband number
one. ותעקרנה לנישואין קמאי, Veta'akrena lenisuin kamai, and retroactively uproots the first
marriage, not the second one, the second one is still good because
a) it's not related to the first and b) you want it
to be good so there's still יבום. yibum. ותתייבם, Vetityabem, and do
יבום. yibum. יש מיאון לאחר מיתה במקום מצוה, Yesh miun le'achar mita
bimkom mitzvah, here's the question. Guy number one died on her, but
can... will we allow her to go back to a marriage she
had five years ago that the guy died on her in order
to allow an יבום yibum here, במקום מצוה, bimkom mitzvah, although as
Dove points out rightly it's only a יבום דרבנן yibum derabbanan because
she's a קטנה. ktana. Okay, so will we allow her to look
back at an old marriage from five years ago where the guy
died and since then she's been married to another guy and go
ahead and retroactively undermine that
marriage?
You see like מיאון...
miun... a posthumous מיאון miun במקום מצוה bimkom mitzvah או לא, o
lo, or not. שחו שני בני אדם בארבע אמות זו ובאו ושאלו
את רבי עקיבא בבית האסורים ואסר. Sachu shnei bnei adam be'arba amot
zu uvau vesha'alu et Rabbi Akiva beveit ha'asurim ve'asar. All right, at
that stage, no way, the guy's already dead. כדברי רבי יהודה בן
בתירה ואסר. Kedivrei Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira ve'asar. Anyway, what do you
see? So that was a pretty absurd case and we said no.
But according to Rabbi Yishmael ברבי יוסי, beRabbi Yose, in a normal
scenario if she does מיאון miun with guy number two, that will
redefine her status as no longer having been a גרושה gerusha vis-a-vis
guy number one. So he denied that Rabbi Akiva said no to
that, he said the answer to that is obviously yes. So you
see there's a מחלוקת תנאים machloket tana'im whether מיאון miun with guy
number two makes her a non-גרושה gerusha vis-a-vis guy number one. Let's
wrap this
up. אמר רבי יצחק בר אשיאן ומודה רב שמותרת לאחיו של זה
שנאסרה עליו. Amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Ashian u'modeh Rav shemuteret le'achiv shel
zeh sheniesra alav. Rav would agree
that even though the מיאון miun with guy number two... back to
our simple case, hah, I just gave this to you so you
would appreciate the case we started with. Back to guy... this case,
okay, so here you have, right,
okay, גט, get, then she goes, that's guy number one, then she
goes here to guy number two, okay, and then she's married to
him and then she does מיאון miun and what are we saying?
Guy number one can't take her back. This does not redefine her
status, she remains a גרושה gerusha to guy number one, he can't
take her back. Okay, yes, that's what we're saying. Now let's see
what we're going to say. Again, it's so funny that the גמרא
Gemara so much thinks that מיאון miun of guy number two should
work and keeps on pushing pulling us in that direction. So we're
going to say like this. אמר רבי יצחק בר אשיאן ומודה רב
שמותרת לאחיו של זה שנאסרה
עליו.
Amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Ashian u'modeh Rav shemuteret le'achiv shel zeh
sheniesra alav. Even though she... him cannot go back to guy number
one, you know who she can now marry? Guy number one's brother.
Now if this... she was really גרושה, gerusha, she could never marry
guy... I mean even
גרושה דרבנן, gerusha derabbanan, right, she's גרושת אחיו, grushat achiv, my brother's
ex-wife, I can't marry her. But no, מיאון miun really do... even
of guy number two, really does redefine her status even vis-a-vis guy
number one. one and we really say she's never considered to have
been married to him, and therefore she can marry the brother. The
only thing we don't allow is for her to go back to
guy number one because because
we're
afraid that guy number one is going to try to ruin the
marriage with guy number two like we said. So again, really amazing
how much גמרא's Gemara pulling to say that the מיאון mi'un even
of guy number two in principle works. So even when we see
she can't go back to guy number one because we're afraid he'll
ruin the marriage, she's really not going to be defined as a
גרושה grusha and she can really go ahead and marry the guy's
brother. Okay, by the way, what it doesn't explore is can she
therefore marry a כהן, kohen, right? Which seemed like the answer should
be yes.
Can she do מיאון בעל כרחו? mi'un ba'al korcho?
Yeah, that's the classic case.
Okay, so then it's understandable that maybe she could do it even
after he's dead retroactively.
Yeah, except, yeah but then the whole but then do
you
still have a marriage to relate to, to do מיאון? mi'un? Anyway,
ומודה רב שאסורה לאחין של זה שנאסרה עליו. U'modeh Rav she'asura l'achiv
shel zeh shenesra alav. פשיטא. Pshita. It's so funny. Obviously, not obviously
by any stretch, but okay. הוא ניהו דמכיר במיזתה ובקריצתה, Hu nihu
d'makir be'mizatah u'v'kritzatah, right? It's, you know, he's the one, by him
we're afraid that she notices he can see his hand signals and
we're afraid to let her go back to the guy because he's
going to try to seduce her and signal her to do מיאון
mi'un so that she can come back to him. Okay, and we're
afraid of him ruining the second marriage. אבל אחיו לא, Aval achiv
lo, but we're not concerned about that by the brother. So in
principle we're saying the מיאון mi'un of guy number two works, it's
just we don't let her go back to guy number one.
מהו דתימא נגזור האי אטו האי קא משמע לן. mahu d'teima nigzor
hai atu hai ka mashma lan. No, I admit that that's true,
but I might be concerned let's at least make a גזירה, gezeira,
once we're אוסרין ossering her to guy number one we should לאסור
osser her to the brothers. No, we don't. We only לאסור osser
her to guy number one, but in principle we really consider her
to not be a גרושה. grusha. ואיכא דאמרי, v'ika d'amri, some say,
אמר רב יוסף בר אשיאן, Amar Rav Yosef Bar Ashian, כשם שאסורה
לו כך אסורה לאחיו. keshem she'asura lo kach asura l'achiv. He is
forbidden to the brothers. הני הוא דמכיר בקריצתם
ומיזתם, hanni hu d'makir be'kritzatam u'mizatatam, but why? She doesn't recognize their
signals and we're not afraid that they'll ruin the marriage, the marriage
to guy number two. גזירה אחיו אטו הוא. gezeira achiv atu hu.
We're afraid the brothers will lead to this. So again quite fascinating
that גמרא Gemara thinks that in principle if she does מיאון mi'un
to guy number two it should completely redefine her status. The only
problem of going back to guy number one is we're afraid
guy number one will try to ruin the marriage with guy number
two. Okay, and again what was not explored was מיאון mi'un after
גט get vis-a-vis defining her status as a גרושה grusha for a
כהן. kohen. That was not explored. Yes.
If there was no גט get from the first husband, she just
did מיאון mi'un with him and then she did מיאון mi'un with
the second husband, she can then she can go back to the
first?
Totally. Of course, yeah. Okay, let's get on to a new point.
משנה: Mishna: המגרש
את האשה ויחזירה. Hamigaresh et ha'isha v'yachzira. See here's again the case
about מחזיר גרושתו. machzir grushato. But this was without being married to
anybody in between. Did גירושין, gerushin, remarried her. מותרת ליבם. Muteret l'yavam.
She is permissible. Now here we're back to a straight forget מיאון,
mi'un, forget מיאון, mi'un, we're back to now oh good we can
talk about ייבום, yibum, we don't have to worry about מיאון. mi'un.
Anyway, so we're not dealing with מיאון mi'un anymore, we're dealing with
the simple case of ייבום. yibum. Okay, so גדולה, gdola, right? Simple
case of a גדולה, gdola, here they are, full size, okay, they're
married, full size, okay, גט, get, okay, that's stage number one. Then
stage number two is they get back together. Yay, they get remarried,
okay, and then he dies. And now we've got the brother. So
here's the question: is she אשת אחיו המת eshet achiv hamet and
there's a מצוה mitzvah of ייבום yibum or do we say at
this stage when he gave her a גט, get, you know what
her status was vis-a-vis the brother? גרושת אחיו grushat achiv and an
ערוה. ervah. So when they get remarried does that redefine her status
vis-a-vis the brother and now he looks at her only through the
lens of the second marriage and it's אשת אחיו המת, eshet achiv
hamet, or does once already over here she's already גרושת אחיו grushat
achiv and remains an ערוה ervah to him even at this stage?
She was גרושת אחיו grushat achiv in a latent stage that then
comes back when he dies?
Oh here? Yeah not latent, I mean it would be latent. She's
always גרושת אחיו grushat achiv even when he remarries her. She still
as far as him she still remains גרושת אחיו. grushat achiv.
It's like saying she's an אשת אבי, eshet avi, right? How can
he marry her, she was always an אשת אבי. eshet avi.
Well
because גרושת אחיו grushat achiv is like
a anyway but the answer is it's not a problem. Okay, המגרש
את האשה ויחזירה מותרת ליבם. Hamigaresh et ha'isha v'yachzira muteret l'yavam. Then
it is permissible to do ייבום. yibum. She's not גרושת אחיו. grushat
achiv. ורבי אליעזר אוסר. V'Rabbi Eliezer oser. But Rabbi Eliezer says no,
sorry, she remains אסור assur to him. Okay. וכן המגרש את היתומה
ויחזירה מותרת ליבם. V'chen hamigaresh et ha'yetoma v'yachzira muteret l'yavam.
Let's say you have the same case except it was with a
minor. Okay, so it was this קידושין דרבנן. kedushin d'rabbanan.
Why minor? יתומה. yetoma.
יתומה, yetoma,
יתומה yetoma means that yeah the reason we're talking about יתומה yetoma
that it's an interesting case is the father is dead and therefore
it's קידושין דרבנן. kedushin d'rabbanan. She's a minor. It's not interesting if
she's an adult יתומה, yetoma, right? יתומה yetoma in the This context
means she's a minor, the father is dead, so it's קידושין דרבנן,
Kiddushin d'Rabbanan, right? Is that clear? If the father is alive, it's
the קידושין דאורייתא. Kiddushin d'Oraisa. So then we get back to our
מיאון mi'un scenarios. If similarly, if she was a minor and it
was קידושין דרבנן Kiddushin d'Rabbanan and he divorced her and remarried her,
okay, so now we're in דרבנן d'Rabbanan territory, מותרת ליבם. muteres l'yabam.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אוסר. oser. Now you and I are probably
saying okay why is that case any different, like why is that
an interesting different case? So now we're going to see why it's
an interesting different case because of case number three. קטנה שהשיאה אביה,
Ketanah she'hisi'ah aviha, she's not a יתומה, yesomah, her father married her
off when she was a קטנה, ketanah, so that's קידושין דאורייתא. Kiddushin
d'Oraisa. Everybody with me? ונתגרשה, V'nisgareshah, now she was divorced, גרושה דאורייתא.
gerushah d'Oraisa. Now כיתומה בחיי האב, k'yesomah b'chayei ha'av, here's an important
phrase, an orphan while the father is alive. By orphan it means
she is no longer under the father's control. What is a minor,
right, what is a minor who is no longer under her father's
control? She was married to another guy and then she's under her
husband's control, but then the guy divorces her or dies. So now
she's left her father's house, no longer in her husband's house. She's
emancipated, emancipated six year old, right, who's been being married off and
then her husband dies on her, but she is now no longer
under her father's control, כיתומה
בחיי האב.
k'yesomah
b'chayei ha'av.
She's not under her mother's or brother's control either.
No, they could still marry her off. It seems like it. Okay,
that yes it was yes.
Okay, when she returned to eating תרומה? terumah?
What? I think it's a good point. When she returned to eating...
you guys are confusing me, but okay let's finish the משנה. Mishnah.
Actually you're right though if the father's around and he can't דרבנן
d'Rabbanan marry her, why could the... but see what anyway yeah...
if she's a בת כהן bas kohein then doesn't she return to
her father?
You mean בית אביה beis aviha in terms of the eating תרומה
terumah that even after... yes that's a good point that even though
the husband dies she's considered still going back to the household in
terms of the issue of eating תרומה terumah but in terms of
the father being able to like you know to control her destiny,
marry her off, but it's a good point she's part of the
father's household but that's not the same as being under the father's
control. Yes, that's a very good point and that the תרומה terumah
shows that. Okay, so she went ahead, she was married דאורייתא d'Oraisa
by the father, the guy divorced her, כיתומה בחיי האב, k'yesomah b'chayei
ha'av, and then what happened? והחזירה, V'hechzirah, the guy remarries her. But
this remarrying is now only a דרבנן d'Rabbanan remarrying because it's with
a minor, okay? דברי הכל אסורה ליבם. Divrei hakol asurah l'yabam. Then
if this was the case, right, she it was a קידושין דאורייתא,
Kiddushin d'Oraisa, she was a minor, she was married by the father,
but it was קידושין דאורייתא, Kiddushin d'Oraisa, okay, okay, because it's דאורייתא,
d'Oraisa, because she's married by the father. And then she gets a
גט, get, and then he remarries her, okay? So at this stage
once there's a גט get she's גרושת אחיו דאורייתא gerushas achiv d'Oraisa
because this was a דאורייתא d'Oraisa marriage, right? When he remarries her
it doesn't redefine her דאורייתא d'Oraisa status, right, because it's only a
קידושין דרבנן. Kiddushin d'Rabbanan. So that case well everybody agrees, that case
everybody agrees that she really is גרושת אחיו gerushas achiv and there's
no מצוה mitzvah of ייבום. yibum. Okay and now
you understand why רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer might not like the other
cases, because they might all because this case might be the case
he's really concerned about, right, because this case it's a real דאורייתא.
d'Oraisa. And Michael raises an interesting question, which is if the father
can't marry her off דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, who's marrying her off the second
time? So according to the רמב"ם, Rambam, I mentioned it to you
before, the רמב"ם Rambam doesn't mention mother and brothers, so it could
be that she's marrying herself off, or maybe the father can marry
her off דרבנן d'Rabbanan but not דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, I don't know, it's
an interesting question who's marrying her off the second time.
And the גיטין Gittin וכתובות v'Kesubos establishes that once the father does
קידושין Kiddushin with a קטנה ketanah daughter and that marriage then dissolves,
he loses all power over... right, correct.
But the interesting question is who's marrying her off the second time?
Is she doing it herself or is the father doing it דרבנן
d'Rabbanan the same way the mother and the brothers can do it
דרבנן? d'Rabbanan? I don't know the answer to that. Okay let's take
a look.
And you don't do חליצה. chalitzah.
You don't do... yeah exactly because she's גרושת אחיו. gerushas achiv. אמר
איפא, Amar Eifa, well
we'll see whether you do חליצה. chalitzah. Hold on, okay that's gonna
come up.
אמר איפא,
Amar
Eifa, מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר? mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Eliezer? Why does רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer not like it even in the first cases where
she was a גדולה gedolah who got divorced and remarried? Okay
here's the reason. הואיל ועמדה לו שעה אחת באיסורא, Ho'il v'amdah lo
sha'ah achas b'issura, because there was a moment then she was גרושת
אחיו, gerushas achiv, so then presumably she's gonna remain גרושת אחיו gerushas
achiv even after the remarrying. אמרו ליה רבנן לאיפא, Amru lei rabanan
l'Eifa,
so the rabbis said to איפא, Eifa, אי הכי ee hachi חליצה
נמי לא תיבעי, chalitzah nami lo tibei, exactly the question Michael asked.
If that's true that she really is according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer a גרושת אחיו דאורייתא gerushas achiv d'Oraisa and that doesn't change
even after the second marriage, so then she shouldn't even need חליצה.
chalitzah. Okay וכי תימא v'chi teima הכי נמי, hachi nami, okay maybe
that's true. No, והתניא בברייתא, v'ha tanyah b'raisa, we learned in a
ברייתא, Braisa, משום דרבי אליעזר אמרו, mishum d'Rabbi Eliezer amru, in the
name of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer they said, חולצת, chalotzes, she still
has to do חליצה. chalitzah. So even though רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says that she's אסור, assur, right, you can't just say he simply
just rules that she's גרושת אחיו gerushas achiv and the marriage doesn't
redefine. He obviously... He obviously has some type of דרבנן d'rabbanan or
ספק safek thing going on around because he still demands חליצה. chalitza.
So what's that about? אלא אמר איפא, ella amar Eifa, so Rabbi
Eifa said, רבי אליעזר לא ידעינן מאי טעמיה. Rabbi Eliezer lo yadan
mai ta'amei. Okay, I give up. I don't know what his reason
is. אמר אביי היינו טעמיה דרבי אליעזר, amar Abaye hainu ta'amei d'Rabbi
Eliezer, I'll tell you what Rabbi Eliezer's reason is. מספקא ליה, misafka
lei, okay, he has a doubt. אי מיתה מפיל אי נשואין ראשונים
מפילין, ee misah mapil ee nisuin rishonim mapilin, what defines her status
vis-a-vis יבום? yibum? So now we'll deal with the case by the
adult, okay, back there being an adult, he becomes גרושת אחיו grushas
achiv and then she gets remarried and then and then he dies,
right? So, when now there's a מצוה mitzva of יבום, yibum, right,
what defines, meaning one way to say it is her status sticks
with her and it doesn't get overwritten by a second marriage. So
it's a question about what defined her personal status. But he's saying
what defines the מצוה mitzva of יבום, yibum, right? When she, when
he dies, is it that his death, now she becomes like the,
now the מצוה mitzva of יבום yibum is defined? Or is it
from the moment that this woman is married to his brother, right,
that defines all relevant laws for הלכות hilchos for יבום, yibum, as
soon as they got married? So therefore, once they got divorced, she's
out of the יבום yibum category, because as soon as they got
married, we started thinking, oh this is a potential יבום yibum scenario.
So her יבום yibum status started being assessed here and therefore once
she got the גט get she was out of the category of
יבום, yibum, or did her יבום yibum status start being assessed only
after the guy died and then she is in the פרשה parsha
of יבום? yibum?
Okay, because it's the whole point of the כי ישבו אחים יחדיו
ki yeishvu achim yachdav and, at the end of the day, he's
dead and there's no...
I understand, how much you know, whatever, when you get to הלכה
halacha you deal with these formal questions, you don't always go straight
back to the reason of it. Okay, so anyway, so what's the
reason? All right, fine. So, that he doesn't know. So if you
go, if it's assessed by the first marriage, then she's a גרושת
אחיו grushas achiv and there's no מצוה. mitzva. If it's by the
second marriage, there is. So basically he doesn't know whether to give
her that status of גרושת אחיו grushas achiv or not.
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
right, אי מיתה מפיל אי נשואין ראשונים מפילין. ee misah mapil ee
nisuin rishonim mapilin.
If you go by the death and then you assess her status,
then there's a מצוה mitzva of יבום. yibum. She's the wife of
the dead brother. ואי נשואין ראשונים מפילין, v'ee nisuin rishonim mapilin, if
you look at the first marriage, from the moment they get married
you assess her status, השתא דאתיא לידי איסורא, hashta d'asya l'yadei issura,
and if you start assessing it at the first marriage, then she's
defined as גרושת אחיו. grushas achiv. So that's a good point, meaning
yeah, let's maybe you go by the first status and if it's
a ספק safek you play it safe, you do חליצה. chalitza. That's
Rabbi Eliezer's position. רבא אמר לעולם פשיטא ליה לרבי אליעזר דמיתה מפיל.
Rava amar l'olam peshita l'Rabbi Eliezer d'misah mapil. No, no, no, it's
clear that you go by the time of death and she's not
in principle גרושת אחיו. grushas achiv. So therefore what's his problem? And
there's a מצוה mitzva of יבום. yibum. ומיהו, umihu, it's a דרבנן
d'rabbanan problem, right? Once you say you do חליצה chalitza and not
יבום, yibum, there's two possibilities: either you're going to have a ספק
safek what the status is and therefore it's a play-it-safe move, or
there's going to be some דרבנן d'rabbanan problem. And because there's some
דרבנן d'rabbanan problem, you can't let her walk away because there's still
a דאורייתא d'oraisa issue, but you can never do יבום, yibum, so
therefore you do חליצה. chalitza. So Rava's going to take the דרבנן
d'rabbanan approach. הכל בקיאין בגירושין ואין הכל בקיאין בחזרה. hakol beki'in b'geirushin
v'ein hakol beki'in b'hazara. Everybody knows she got divorced, not everybody knows
she got remarried. So therefore if he does יבום, yibum, they'll say,
"Oh my God, he's doing יבום! yibum! She was a divorcee from
the guy. You still do יבום yibum after the guy divorces her
and dies?" They won't know about the... that there's a מצוה mitzva
of יבום yibum after divorce.
I wouldn't think that.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אדרבה, adeiraba, the opposite is true, more
people know about marriage than גט. get. חזרה כיון דיתבא תותיה אית
ליה קלא, hazara keivan d'yasra tusei is lei kala, when he remarries
her, they're living together, so people know about it. So therefore what
are you talking about? People know about the divorce and don't know
about the גט. get. I mean, don't know about the divorce and
don't know about the remarrying. No, there are scenarios where that could
be true. מי לא עסקינן, mi lo askinan, we could also be
talking about cases דהדרא באורתא, d'hazra b'ursa, that he remarried her at
night, ושכיב דצפרא, ushchiv d'tzafra, and he died the next morning. So
there could be scenarios where it was known she was divorced and
nobody had heard about the remarrying and therefore we cannot allow יבום,
yibum, we have to demand חליצה. chalitza. Okay, so we have two
answers so far about Rabbi Eliezer, why he would say חליצה. chalitza.
One is he has a ספק, safek, maybe she really is גרושת
אחיו. grushas achiv. The other's a דרבנן, d'rabbanan, people might not know
of her new status. רב אשי אמר היינו טעמיה דרבי אליעזר, Rav
Ashi amar hainu ta'amei d'Rabbi Eliezer, here's the reason of Rabbi Eliezer,
דגזר הני משום יתומה בחיי אביה והחזירה, d'gazar hani mishum yesoma b'chayei
aviha v'hazra, which the גמרא's Gemara going to say is very much
פשט pshat of the משנה. mishna. The third case in the משנה
mishna is a case that everybody agrees is a problem, right, when
the father married her off and then she remarried as a קטנה
ketana on her own. Right? There, the second marriage does not redefine
her because the second marriage is only Rabbinic, right? Everybody remember that
case, right? So because that case is clearly a problem, she's clearly
גרושת אחיו grushas achiv because she was really married to
the guy דאורייתא d'oraisa and then the guy divorced her, and then
she got remarried only דרבנן. d'rabbanan. Since that case is clearly a
problem, Rabbi Eliezer doesn't allow any case that looks like that because
to protect against that case.
Okay,
so the first case...
No, so since that's the case by קטנה ktana by that the
father married her off, Rabbi Elazar doesn't allow any case, even when
she's a גדולה gedolah at both stages or יתומה yesoma at both
stages, to protect against this case.
Right, but that seems a little far-fetched though.
Whatever, it's a classic דרבנן de-rabbanan extension גזירה gzera and so on.
Okay, so that's what he says.
קטן וגדול katan v'gadol different animal.
All right. היינו דתני רב אלעזר hainu d'sani Rav Elazar דגזר הני
משום יתומה בחיי אביה והחזירה. degazar hani mishum yesoma b'chayei aviha v'hichzirah.
הכי נמי מסתברא, hachi nami mistavra, that makes sense that it's all
an extension of the last case. הכי נמי דתני סיפא, hachi nami
detani seifa, because the end of the משנה mishna says קטנה שהשיאה
אביה ונתגרשה כיתומה בחיי האב והחזירה ktana shehisi’ah aviha v'nisgarsha k'yesoma b'chayei
ha-av v'hichzirah דברי הכל divrei ha-kol אסורה ליבם. asura l’yavam.
Everybody agrees in the last case when she's married by a father
and then remarried. So האי מאי למימרא, hai mai l'meimra, why do
you have to say that? פשיטא, pishita, of course, of course that
case she's a גרושת אחיו. grushas achiv. The second marriage doesn't redefine
her. The second marriage is only דרבנן. de-rabbanan. אלא לאו, ela lav,
the reason to tell me that third case is הא קמשמע לן
ha kamashma lan to frame that that's what the earlier debate was
about, that טעמא דרבי אלעזר ta'ama de-Rabbi Elazar דגזר הני משום האי,
degazar hani mishum hai, that the reason that Rabbi Elazar was forbidding
the first two cases of being a גדולה gedolah at both stages
or יתומה yesoma at both stages was to protect against the third
case that everybody agrees is a problem. שמע מינה, shma mina, that
is a good proof. So all of the positions of Rabbi Elazar
are an extension, are דרבנן, de-rabbanan, and that's why there's חליצה chalitza
but not יבום, yibum, and they're an extension of the final case
of married by the father and then remarried by oneself. So שמע
מינה. shma mina. תני כוותיה דרב אשי, tani k'vosei d'Rav Ashi, we
taught a ברייתא braisa like Rav Ashi that spells it out explicitly.
מודים חכמים לרבי אלעזר modim chachamim l'Rabbi Elazar בקטנה שהשיאה אביה ונתגרשה
הרי היא כיתומה בחיי האב. b'ktana shehisi'ah aviha v'nisgarsha harei hi k'yesoma
b'chayei ha-av. Okay,
the חכמים chachamim agree to Rabbi Elazar in the case where a
minor married by the father and divorced and then she's become like
a יתומה, yesoma, she becomes emancipated as it were. והחזירה, v'hichzirah, and
then she remarried the same guy as a קטנה, ktana, שאסורה ליבם
she-asura l'yavam מפני שגירושיה גירושין
גמורין, mipnei she-geirushia geirushin g'murin, then she's forbidden because the divorce was
a full divorce, it was based on a קידושין דאורייתא, kiddushin de-oraisa,
so she's a full status of גרושת אחיו. grushas achiv. ואין חזרתה
חזרה גמורה, v'ein chazarasah chazara gmura,
and the remarriage is not a דאורייתא de-oraisa remarriage, it's only a
דרבנן. de-rabbanan. Since anyway it says the חכמים chachamim agree to Rabbi
Eliezer, it seems to very much frame it that this is the
concern of Rabbi Eliezer and this is what the whole position of
Rabbi Eliezer is about. במה דברים אמורים, bamei devarim amurim, when is
that true? שגירשה כשהיא קטנה והחזירה כשהיא קטנה, she-geirshah k'she-hi ktana v'hichzirah
k'she-hi ktana,
when he divorced her when she was a minor and after the
father married her off and then remarried as a minor, so it
was only a קידושין דרבנן kiddushin de-rabbanan and therefore does not redefine
her status. אבל גירשה כשהיא קטנה, aval geirshah k'she-hi ktana, if he
divorced her as a minor so she's a גרושת אחיו דאורייתא. grushas
achiv de-oraisa. והחזירה כשהיא גדולה, v'hichzirah k'she-hi gedolah,
but remarried her as an adult. So if he remarried her as
an adult, that does redefine her status, right? Because then it's a
קידושין דאורייתא. kiddushin de-oraisa. אי נמי החזירה כשהיא קטנה וגדלה אצלו, i
nami hichzirah k'she-hi ktana v'gadla etzlo,
or remarried her as a minor but then she became an adult
while, you know, you know, before he died. So the assumption is,
and this is a good discussion we're going to get into right
away, that even after the קידושי קטנה, kiddushei ktana, if they stay
married through the period of her becoming an adult, then it becomes
a קידושין דאורייתא, kiddushin de-oraisa, presumably because then they're having sex once
she's an adult and that sex is considered like ביאת קידושין. bias
kiddushin. Okay? Let's not worry about that. Okay, so in that case,
so basically when is it true that there's a problem that she
remains גרושת אחיו? grushas achiv? If he remarried her as a קטנה
ktana and he died before she became an adult. But if he
remarried her as an adult or she became an adult after they
were remarried, then it becomes a קידושין דאורייתא kiddushin de-oraisa the second
time around as well and redefines her status. Okay? So in that
case, או חולצת או מתיבמת, o choletzes o misyabemes, she could do
either חליצה chalitza or יבום. yibum. משום רבי אלעזר אמרו, mishum Rabbi
Elazar amru, but no, Rabbi Elazar once again says I'm not playing
around. Once you have that scenario, I don't care. חולצת ולא מתיבמת,
choletzes v'lo misyabemes, she's got to do חליצה. chalitza. So it seems
very clear the Rabbi Elazar's position is to protect the case that
everybody agrees is a problem, where the father married her off and
she remarried herself as a קטנה. ktana. Okay, that everybody agrees to
really is גרושת אחיו, grushas achiv, and Rabbi Eliezer is saying therefore
I'm not going to allow any scenario that looks like that to
protect against that case. Okay, now the גמרא gemara wraps up and
it says בעי מיניה רבה מרב נחמן, ba'ei minei Rabbah mi-Rav Nachman,
Rabbah asked Rav Nachman: צרתה מהו? tzarasah mahu?
How about this scenario where Rabbi Elazar does not allow her, right,
let's say the case about the גדולה, gedolah, right, that remarried etc.
Rabbi Elazar does not allow יבום yibum because he's convinced that she
really isn't גרושת אחיו grushas achiv but because of the קטנה ktana
case he's not going to allow יבום. yibum. Okay, what about if
there's another wife? Wife-in-law, Rabbi Dov liked that phrase. What if there's
another wife? Can he do יבום yibum with the other wife or
not? Right? Remember, her status according to Rabbi Elazar at least דרבנן
de-rabbanan is גרושת אחיו. grushas achiv. So her status is at least
as a דרבנן ערווה, de-rabbanan erva, right?
Yeah, but the first guy, could the first guy then do יבום?
yibum? Now, not the first guy. He's got two wives. This guy
who died. He's the same guy. He's the same guy, okay? He
just remarried her. He died, right? That's why she's redefining the status
because he remarried her. He dies. So according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, at least דרבנן, derabanan, she's got a גרושת אחיו grushas achiv
status to protect against the case of the קטנה, ketana, right? So
can he do יבום yibum with the צרה? tzara? Would that be
a case of צרת ערווה tzaras erva דרבנן? derabanan? Or would he
say this whole thing is just a גזירה gezeira because of the
קטנה ketana case, so we're not going to prevent him from doing
יבום yibum with the co-wife?
Okay? Sort of like we have with the מיאון miun thing though,
like you know, you might then even give her...
Fine. So that's exactly, so that's the question. Let's take a look.
מהו? mahu? אמר אי, amar i, היא גופא גזירה ואנן ניקום ונגזור
גזירה לגזירה? hi gufa gezeira veanan neikum venigzar gezeira legezeira? הגזירה? hagezeira?
The whole thing is a גזירה. gezeira. The whole thing, right? The
whole thing, to not allow him according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
to do יבום yibum with her is because, you know, to protect
against these scenarios. Okay, so we don't really make her, you know,
an ערווה דרבנן. erva derabanan. We just don't allow you to do
it with her, but you can go ahead and do יבום yibum
with the co-wife.
והתניא vehatanya משום רבי אליעזר אמרו היא וצרתה חולצות. mishum Rabbi Eliezer
amru hi vetzarasah choletzos. היא ו hi ve... so wait, we get
a ברייתא. braisa. The ברייתא braisa says that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says that she and the co-wife have to do חליצה. chalitza. So
first the גמרא Gemara says, wait a minute, היא וצרתה סלקא דעתך
דחולצות? hi vetzarasah salka dachas decholetzos? What do you mean, she and
the co-wife? You don't have to do חליצה chalitza with both wives.
אלא לאו או היא או צרתה חולצת? ela lav o hi o
tzarasah choletzas? All right, it means either she or the co-wife does
חליצה. chalitza. But nevertheless, it says you got to do חליצה chalitza
with the co-wife. גמרא Gemara says, no. לאו דתרצתא כמתרצתא? lav detartzata
kimetartzata? Wait a minute, you've already fixed the ברייתא braisa by saying
the ו vav means or and not and. So once you're already
editing the ברייתא, braisa, let's edit it a little more.
תרצה הכי: taretz hachi: היא חולצת צרתה או חולצת או מתייבמת. hi
choletzas tzarasah o choletzas o misyabemes. The co-wife, you can do either.
Okay, but again, this gets to this question of how much when
we're saying according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer he can't do, he
can't do יבום, yibum, are we saying just דרבנן derabanan don't do
יבום, yibum, but we're not saying that she has the status of
an ערווה erva and therefore go ahead you can do יבום yibum
with the צרה? tzara? That's what the גמרא Gemara is saying. As
concluded, the alternative would be saying whatever motivated רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer
גזירה, gezeira, whatever רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer didn't want you because of
the קטנה ketana scenario or whatever, at the end of the day,
he's considering her at least דרבנן derabanan as a גרושת אחיו. grushas
achiv. And once he's considering her a גרושת אחיו, grushas achiv, so
you can't do it with the צרה tzara either. It's a צרת
ערווה tzaras erva case, right? But the גמרא Gemara is saying not
that way. That you can actually wind up doing יבום yibum with
the צרה. tzara. Okay, so that was that case about divorce and
remarry, and a very important question in יבום, yibum, whether it's נישואין
ראשונים nisuin rishonim or whether it's מיתה misa that's מפלת.
mappeles. She goes back into the מיאון miun to him.
All right, next case. Next משנה. mishna. שני אחים נשואים לשתי אחיות
קטנות. shnei achim nesuim lishtei achayos ketanos. Okay, so now we've laid
the background. We've talked about מיאון, miun, we've reintroduced יבום, yibum, now
we're going to talk about מיאון miun and יבום yibum together. All
right. So you got two brothers married to two minor sisters. ומת
בעלה של אחת מהן, umeis baalah shel achas meihen, and one of
the husbands dies, הלזו תצא משום אחות אשה. halazu seitzei mishum achos
isha. So that's a simple case. You've got to love it when
I start saying simple cases about this. Okay, so that's the case
about... Maybe it's straight...
Finally we can get back to our ראובן Reuven and שמעון. Shimon.
Okay,
so here's ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon married to רחל Rachel
and
לאה. Leah.
Okay,
and they're קטנות, ketanos, so it's דרבנן. derabanan. And one of these
guys dies. Okay, so he... This is a case of they're both
in the same category, right? They're both at the דרבנן derabanan level.
So, to the same degree that she's his wife, and that and
same degree that she's his brother's wife, it's all at the דרבנן
derabanan level. But it's also a, but it's also his wife's sister.
Right, that's actually דאורייתא deoraisa wife's sister. What? No, no, no. Not
a father. Classic, back to the case of where מיאון miun is
possible. They're... Okay, so in that case, obviously, you know, she walks
away. And you don't even have to do חליצה. chalitza. You know
why you don't have to do חליצה? chalitza? Because there's no דאורייתא
deoraisa מצוה mitzvah here. It's all within the דרבנן derabanan world. דרבנן
derabanan he's married to her, דרבנן derabanan she's married to him, דרבנן
derabanan there's a מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibum. It's all existing in
the equal דרבנן derabanan world. So within that דרבנן derabanan world, the
same degree that there's a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum because they
were married is the same degree that there's not a מצוה mitzvah
of יבום yibum because it's אחות אשה. achos isha. So she just
walks away in that case.
I'm sorry, really sorry. Why? If these are קטנות, ketanos, so I
don't assume that these are קידושין דאורייתא kiddushin deoraisa that the father...
No, no, no. No father, no father. Okay? We're assuming, the side
actually has the גירסא יתומות קטנות, girsa yesomos ketanos, by the way.
Okay,
fine. I understand. I'm just saying the assumption here is it's not
interesting if there's a father, then it's just a class... might as
well be an adult. The classic cases are here that we're dealing
with קטנות ketanos that there's no father. Okay? So, in this
case... וכן שייך חרשות, v'chein sheyach charashos, and
same thing would be if they're not קטנות ktanos but חרשות. charashos.
The הגר"א ha'Gra takes that out. We're not dealing with חרש cheresh
now, fine. But חרש cheresh is also חידוש דרבנן. chidush derabbanan. Let's
not worry about that. Now, here it becomes interesting. גדולה וקטנה. gedolah
u'ketanah. Okay. So,
you've got—we'll make Leah the גדולה, gedolah, I guess. Okay. So you've
got one of them is the is an adult and the other
is a minor. Now it's going to be interesting because this is
קידושין דאורייתא, kidushin de'oraisa, right? So what's going to be the story?
So who dies? גדולה וקטנה gedolah u'ketanah ומת בעלה של קטנה. u'meis
baalah shel ketanah. Okay. So Reuven dies. Now,
does he have a mitzvah—he has a מצוות יבום דרבנן, mitzvas yibum
derabbanan, this was only קידושין דרבנן, kidushin derabbanan, right? He has an
איסור issur of אחות אשה דאורייתא, achos isha de'oraisa, right? This is
his real wife, right? And this is his wife's sister. Okay. So
he's got a יבום דרבנן yibum derabbanan and אחות אשה דאורייתא. achos
isha de'oraisa. So that's easy. So she's an ערווה, erva, no מצוות
יבום. mitzvas yibum. Walk away.
Okay. תצא קטנה משום אחות אשה. teitzei ketanah mishum achos ishah. The
קטנה ketanah walks away. She's a עריות. arayos. Now, ומת בעלה של
גדולה. u'meis baalah shel gedolah. What if it's the opposite, right? What
if Shimon is the one who died? Okay. Now, here we've got
a problem.
She—this—he has a דאורייתא de'oraisa מצווה mitzvah of יבום, yibum, right? Brother's
דאורייתא de'oraisa wife. דאורייתא de'oraisa מצוות יבום. mitzvas yibum. But he's דרבנן
derabbanan married to the sister and there's a דרבנן derabbanan problem of
אחות אשה, achos ishah, right? So דאורייתא de'oraisa מצוות יבום, mitzvas yibum,
דרבנן derabbanan אחות אשה. achos ishah.
So,
and what can he do?
We'll say, oh, do חליצה chalitzah and stay married to your wife.
No, then your wife
becomes—becomes אחות חלוצתו. achos chalutzaso. Divorce your wife and do יבום yibum
here. No, then she becomes אחות גרושתו. achos grushaso. So there's no
way out of it, okay? It's not עריות דאורייתא arayos de'oraisa that
she can just walk away because this is the דאורייתא de'oraisa and
this is the דרבנן. derabbanan. There's not a דאורייתא de'oraisa ערווה erva
that she can walk away. There is a דאורייתא de'oraisa obligation of
יבום. yibum. Anything you do will make the other one forbidden. You
divorce her, she's אחות גרושתו. achos grushaso. You do חליצה chalitzah to
her, she's אחות
גרושתו.
achos
grushaso.
So there's no halachic method in the גמרא. gemara. Why—why won't the
דאורייתא חיוב de'oraisa chiyuv override the איסור דרבנן? issur derabbanan?
Well, you have to do something. It doesn't just disappear. It's not
like you have one חיוב chiyuv and another חיוב chiyuv or whatever.
There's a status here. So what's he going to do? Do יבום
yibum and say he's going to violate as he's living with her,
he's going to be violating אחות אשה דרבנן? achos ishah derabbanan? We
don't want to tolerate that. It's not like a question of like,
oh, two competing mitzvos, which one am I going to do, you
know, or like even like a momentary issue like can I be
over on an איסור דרבנן issur derabbanan because of a case of
חולה choleh on שבת? shabbos? Like, you do יבום yibum for her,
then he's going to be, you know, in that act of יבום,
yibum, I mean, he's going to be constantly sort of in a
contradiction here. If he stays married to her, that's going to be
the case, that's what's going to be what the משנה mishnah suggests.
But those questions could be stated as why don't you say that
במקום מצוה לא גזרו רבנן? be'makom mitzvah lo gazru rabbanan?
Yeah, so again, you could say the Rabbis like make it go
off, but you know, but then it sort of like undermines the
whole sort of status and institution. So we want to sort of
play it through, treat this as a serious institution, we have to
deal sort of how we're going to deal with the consequence. So
let's see what the משנה mishnah says. Now you can appreciate the
quandary here. So, ומת בעלה של גדולה. u'meis baalah shel gedolah. ר'
אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer אומר omer מלמדין את הקטנה שתמאן בו. melamdin es
haktanah shetemaein bo. He's got an easy solution. Teach her to do
מיאון, miun, she completely is out of the picture, they were never
married, magic, and now he can go ahead and do יבום. yibum.
Okay. What? Why did I assume the father was dead? Oh, so
that's why we—they asked before. No, no. We're all assuming that the
father's dead. If the father's alive, then it's קידושין דאורייתא. kidushin de'oraisa.
Then it's not an interesting case, right? The only reason this is
an interesting case is because the father is dead, so it's קידושין
דרבנן. kidushin derabbanan. Okay. So you teach her to do מיאון. miun.
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel אומר omer מיאנה מיאנה. me'anah me'anah. If she
wants to do מיאון, miun, great. That'll solve it. We're not going
to tell her to do מיאון. miun. ואם לאו, ve'im lav,
and if not, תמתין עד שתגדיל, tamtin ad shetagdil, wait until she
becomes an adult. ותצא הלזו משום אחות אשה. v'seitzei halazu mishum achos
ishah. So you wait till Rachel becomes an adult. Once Rachel becomes
an adult, the קידושין kidushin become a דאורייתא קידושין de'oraisa kidushin because
they're sleeping together and whatever, it becomes a דאורייתא קידושין. de'oraisa kidushin.
And then she's waiting around, she's not getting remarried. Okay. Once she
becomes an adult, then she's really married to her and then you're
עריות arayos and then she walks away without חליצה. chalitzah.
She might be an עגונה agunah for some number of years.
Exactly. Okay, now the other thing is, one minute, she only became
an עריות, arayos, an אחות אשה achos ishah after the מצוות יבום
mitzvas yibum began, right? The מצוות יבום mitzvas yibum started, then you
waited ten years, and then she became אחות אשה. achos ishah. Does
that redefine the מצוות יבום mitzvas yibum if that status came later?
We'll worry about that. But the other question is, how do they
stay married to one another?
Doesn't—isn't she אחות זקוקתו? achos zekukaso? Right? Even if you're doing nothing
now, you'll solve it in two years from now. Fine. In two
years. from now she'll be able to walk away, fine. But right
now she's אחות זקוקתו Achose Zikukaso because he's got a relationship to
her as well through זיקה. Zikah. So רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel holds
we're not concerned about זיקה. Zikah. Okay, זיקה Zikah is not strong
enough to create a problem of אחות זקוקתו. Achose Zikukaso. So that's
why he has the solution that you can wait around because he's
not bothered with אחות זקוקתו. Achose Zikukaso. Okay, now רבי יהושע אומר,
Rabbi Yehoshua Omer, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says, I can't solve either,
don't like either of those. Number one, I hold you can't teach
her to do מיאון. Miyun. Number two, I hold that there's a
problem of אחות זקוקתו. Achose Zikukaso. So, if you can't teach her
to do מיאון Miyun and there's a problem of אחות זקוקתו, Achose
Zikukaso, you can't do anything right now, right? You're totally stuck. So
he says, אמר רבי יהושע אוי לי על אשתו אוי לי על
אשת אחיו. Amar Rabbi Yehoshua Oy Li Al Ishto Oy Li Al
Eshes Achiv. Woe to his wife, woe to his brother's wife. Both
of them are going to get, you know, hurt in this process.
מוציא את אשתו בגט ואשת אחיו בחליצה. Motzi Es Ishto B'get V'eshes
Achiv B'chalitzah. He has to both give his wife a גט Get
and his brother's wife חליצה. Chalitzah. And he can't just do one,
because as soon as he does one, the other is אחות חלוצתו
Achose Chalutzaso or אחות גרושתו. Achose Grushaso. Okay, he can't stay married
because it's אחות זקוקתו. Achose Zikukaso. He can't just get rid of,
you know, sort of do thing with one because then the other
is אחות... so he's got to divorce both of them, חליצה Chalitzah
with one, גרושה Grushah with the other, you know, גט Get with
the other, and that's...
Why is the one דאורייתא, De'oraisa, the other is... meaning like if
he just does מוציא את אשתו בגט. Motzi Es Ishto B'get.
Yeah, then she becomes אחות גרושתו. Achose Grushaso.
Right, so then why do you have to do חליצה Chalitzah. with
her?
Because she doesn't... because it's only דרבנן D'rabbanan and there's still a
מצוה דאורייתא, Mitzvah De'oraisa, right. Okay, so let's just get to the
bottom of the page, for, yes, he has his wife.
Can he be married to the minor?
He does חליצה. B'chalitzah No, because she's אחות חלוצתו. Achose Chalutzaso.
Okay, that's forever.
Yeah, same, yes. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ומי שרי. Umi
Shari. Now the גמרא's Gemara's problem here certainly seems like רבי אליעזר's
Rabbi Eliezer's solution is the best, just teach her to do מיאון.
Miyun. But the גמרא's Gemara's bothered with that. ומי שרי, Umi Shari,
is it permissible to teach a woman to do מיאון? Miyun? והתני
בר קפרא לעולם ידבק אדם בשלושה דברים ויתרחק משלושה דברים. V'hatni Bar
Kappara L'olam Yidbak Adam B'shlosha Devarim V'yisrachaik Mi'shlosha Devarim. A person should
cleave to three things and distance himself from three things. ידבק בשלושה
דברים, Yidbak B'shlosha Devarim, בחליצה B'chalitzah that she should prove or sort
of try to do חליצה Chalitzah, rather than יבום, Yibbum, interesting. ובבא
שלום, U'v'hava'as Shalom, bringing peace. ובהפרת נדרים, U'v'haforas Nedarim, annulling vows. ויתרחק
משלושה דברים V'yisrachaik Mi'shlosha Devarim and distance from three things, מן המיאון,
Min Ha'miyun, from מיאון Miyun because maybe, you know, that sort of
maybe undermines the whole קידושין Kiddushin from the beginning. ומן הפקדונות, U'min
Ha'pikdonos, from accepting
what do you call it, like what's the word for that? Rot?
Yeah, objects? What? I know, but there's a word for that. Anyway,
and מן הערבנות, U'min Ha'arvanus, and from being a co-signer. Okay, now
so the גמרא's Gemara's answer is no, מיאון דמצוה שאני. Miyun D'mitzvah
Shani. Of course, we normally don't teach people to do מיאון. Miyun.
But here מיאון Miyun is allowing if the... out of the picture,
it allows for יבום דאורייתא. Yibbum De'oraisa. So here we're going to
teach her to do מיאון Miyun because it allows for him, the
husband, to do a יבום דאורייתא Yibbum De'oraisa and therefore we will
allow it. Of course, if he also says you do חליצה, Chalitzah
it's not allowed. But okay, it's allowing you to get to do
something at the דאורייתא De'oraisa level. גופא, Gufa, now let's go look
at this whole statement. התני בר קפרא לעולם ידבק אדם בשלושה דברים,
Hatni Bar Kappara L'olam Yidbak Adam B'shlosha Devarim, בחליצה כבאבא שאול. B'chalitzah
K'abba Shaul. חליצה Chalitzah. follows the idea of אבא שאול Abba Shaul
that we prefer חליצה. Chalitzah. דתניא דתני ברייתא אבא שאול אומר, D'tanya
D'tani Braisa Abba Shaul Omer, הכונס את יבמתו, Ha'kones Es Yevamto,
somebody who marries his sister-in-law לשם נוי L'shem Noy because she's beautiful,
לשם אישות L'shem Ishus or just because he wants to be married
to her, לשם דבר אחר L'shem Davar Acher or for any other
reason other than just to do the מצוה, Mitzvah, purely for the
sake of the מצוה Mitzvah or להקים שם אחיו, L'hakim Shem Achiv,
כאילו פוגע בערווה, K'ilu Poga B'erva, it's like he's having sex with
a woman who is an ערווה, Erva, like אשת אחיו Eshes Achiv
which is אסור Assur off. The only thing that overrides her forbidden
status as אשת אחיו Eshes Achiv is the מצוה Mitzvah of להקים
שם אחיו. L'hakim Shem Achiv. So when that's not, this is, you
know, אבא שאול's Abba Shaul's position. When that's not his motivation, then
the override, technically it is still overridden by it, but it's deeply
problematic. וקרוב בעיני להיות הולד ממזר, V'karov B'einai L'hiyos Ha'vlad Mamzer, it's
almost as if the child is a ממזר. Mamzer. Okay, that's pretty
harsh statement. ובבא שלום, U'v'hava'as Shalom, and that's why you should always
prefer חליצה. You should also always run after bringing peace. דכתיב בקש
שלום ורדפהו, D'ksiv Bakesh Shalom V'rodfehu,
seek out peace and run after it. Now that should be enough
just according to that פסוק, Passuk, but the גמרא Gemara wants to
elaborate. ואמר רבי אבהו, V'amar Rabbi Abahu, אתיא רדיפה רדיפה, Asya Redifa
Redifa, you make a גזירה שווה Gezirah Shavah running after. כתיב התם
בקש שלום ורדפהו, Ksiv Hasam Bakesh Shalom V'rodfehu, וכתיב הכא, V'ksiv Hacha,
it says over there, רודף צדקה וחסד ימצא חיים צדקה וכבוד, Rodef
Tzedakah Va'chesed Yimtza Chayim Tzedakah V'chavod, that one who runs after צדקה
Tzedakah and righteousness and kindness will find life and righteousness and honor,
life in this world, honor in the world to come. So there's
all this wonderful שכר Schar for running after peace. ובהפרת נדרים, U'v'haforas
Nedarim, annulling vows. כרבי נתן, K'rabbi Natan, like רבי נתן. Rabbi Natan.
תניא רבי נתן אומר הנודר כאילו בנה במה, Tanya Rabbi Natan Omer
Ha'noder K'ilu Bana Bamah, one who makes a vow
is like building an altar when it's אסור Assur to build an
altar when there's a central temple. והמקיימו כאילו הקריב עליו קרבן, V'ha'mekaymo
K'ilu Hikriv Alav Korban, and you fulfill it, oh that's a great
thing I fulfilled the vow? No, it's like bringing a קרבן Korban
on a במה, Bamah, which is not a good thing. Meaning, what
it's really is a beautiful metaphor, because the whole idea of vows
is a seeking out of some form of personal religiosity that you're
not satisfied with the existing system of מצוות Mitzvos and הלכה. Halacha.
and the establishment. You want a personal expression of your own religious
sort of impetus and so you make a vow and you fulfill
it. So you could, so he says, yeah, that's like building a
במה bamah and offering on it, you know, which, you know, if
you're believe in the central institutions, that's a bad thing. That's a
threatening thing. That's your own personal religiosity undermining the more communal and
public institutions, right? If you don't think you have good communal and
public institutions and there's no central בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, maybe you
need to have vows and fulfilling them. So he sees like, you
know, subjectively what you're doing is bringing a קרבן korban and building
an altar and then offering on it, but it's a bad thing
because we shouldn't be doing these. Okay? So it's a fascinating question
about attitudes towards like personal religiosity, you know, when you're sort of
in terms of an establishment religion. Okay, so that's why that's a
bad thing.
So therefore you should annul vows. If you've made them, find a
way to annul. וישתרחק משלושה דברים ve-yistrachak mi-shelosha devarim
and distance yourself from three things: מן המיאונים, min ha-me'unim, מיאונים, me'unim,
which is what we sort of started with. דימא גדלה ומיחרטה de-ma
gadla u-micharta because maybe she'll become an adult and then she'll have
regret. Of course, maybe she'll become an adult and have regret that
she didn't do מיאון me'un and now she's stuck. But I guess
the point is that מיאון me'un is something a person does when
she's a minor, so it's maybe, you know, a dangerous thing to
think that she can fully know what she's doing as a minor.
Again, of course, but maybe it was a wrong thing to be
married anyway, that's why he doesn't like מיאון. me'un.
Okay? מן הפקדונות, min ha-pikdonot, accepting objects to watch. בבר מתא, be-var
mata, somebody who lives in your city.
דביתי כביתי דמי de-veiteih ke-veiteih dami because his house is like your
house, he'll give you something to watch and then he'll come over
and he'll be a guest and whatever and the problem is he'll
steal the thing back and then and then tell you, "Where's that
thing I gave you?" Okay? So if he's if he's hanging around
in your house, it's a little dangerous to accept objects to watch
for him.
I don't know. מן הערבון min ha-aravon and from being like a
cosigner in בארבי של ציון, be-arvei shel Tzion, in the ארבי של
ציון arvei shel Tzion which is basically a place where the where
they people would go after the cosigners before they would go after
the actual debtor. דאמר רבי יצחק, de-amar Rabbi Yitzchak, מאי דכתיב, mai
de-chtiv, what's meant by the verse, רע ירוע כי ערב זר, ra
yero'a ki arav zar, evil after evil because you have been a
sort of intertwined with a foreigner or being read here as an
ערב, arav, you have been a cosigner. רעה אחר רעה תבא למקבלי
גרים, ra'ah achar ra'ah tavo le-mekablei gerim, so we're going to read
it a couple things about the word of ערב. arav. So one
is a very negative statement about גרים. gerim. Evil after evil should
come to those that accept converts. Okay? Because that's ערב זר, arav
zar, like you know, you involve an outsider into your religion. So
one way of reading this is a negative statement about about converts.
And ולערבי של ציון u-le-arvei shel Tzion and these cosigners of this
של ציון shel Tzion which is either a place or refers to
an attitude of that that you're going to have bad stuff because
they're going to come straight after the cosigner, not even go to
the debtor first. ולערבי של ציון u-le-arvei shel Tzion ולתוקע עצמו לדבר
הלכה u-le-tokeia atzmo li-devar halakha and somebody who sticks himself, you know,
in a matter of הלכה. halakha. What does that mean? So let's
just finish this up. So what does that mean? מקבלי גרים כרב
חלבו, mekablei gerim ke-Rabbi Chelbo, accepting גרים, gerim, the idea is that
that's bad is like what רב חלבו Rav Chelbo said. דאמר רב
חלבו, de-amar Rav Chelbo, קשים גרים לישראל כספחת בעור, kashim gerim le-Yisrael
ke-sapachat ba-or, גרים gerim is difficult to Israel as leprosy on the
skin because it says ונספחו, ve-nispechu, they'll like cleave to them and
it's read as ספחת sapachat and גרים gerim are bad things. So
presumably the concern here is is because of backsliding and so on.
Very important though, there are obviously very different attitudes towards גרים gerim
in the גמרא, Gemara, this is the most negative one. And if
you just take a look at one line in תוספות Tosafot that
tones it down a bit. תוספות Tosafot says, רעה רעה תבא למקבלי
גרים, ra'ah ra'ah tavo le-mekablei gerim, אמר ר"י, amar Ri, דהיינו היכא
דמשיאין אותם להתגייר, de-hainu heicha de-mashi'in otam le-hitgayer, that's if you are
trying to proactively persuade them, you're going out and you're proselytizing. Then
you got to watch it because maybe they're not sincere and you're
going to it's just going to come back to bite you. או
שמקבלים אותם מיד, o she-mekablim otam mi-yad, or you accept them without
any due process. אבל אם הן מתאמצים להתגייר, aval im hen mit'amtzim
le-hitgayer, if you push them away and they sort of push, you
know, are insistent and you know, consistently like and persevering, then יש
לנו לקבלם, yesh lanu le-kablam, then we should actually try to accept
them and not only is it acceptable, it's a good thing. שהרי
מצינו שנענשו אברהם יצחק ויעקב שלא קיבלו לתמנע שבאתה להתגייר, she-harei matzinu
she-ne'unshu Avraham Yitzchak ve-Yaakov she-lo kibu le-Timna she-ba'ata le-hitgayer, right, the מדרש
Midrash says that אברהם יצחק ויעקב, Avraham Yitzchak ve-Yaakov, right here was
תמנע, Timna, you know, the, you know, that wanted to convert and
they didn't want or whatever and as a result a lot of
bad things happened. So תוספות Tosafot right away tones down this negative
statement and tries to contextualize it and says it depends on the
circumstances.
עמלק Amalek came from תמנע. Timna. Let's just go back to the
גמרא, Gemara, I know we're a little over, let's just go back.
So that's about the גרים gerim statement. Then it says,
okay,
כספחת, ke-sapachat, ארבי של ציון, arvei shel Tzion, the cosigners of של
ציון. shel Tzion. What does that mean? דעבדי, de-avdi, so it's a-
we sort of do a mnemonic of this word or break up
the word, שלוף דות, shelof dot, remove yourself and then like stick
yourself, which is basically that the actual debtor removes himself from it
and then it's the cosigner that gets stuck with having to pay
the debt. תוקע עצמו לדבר הלכה. tokeia atzmo lidvar halacha. Now what's
this weird thing, sticking yourself on a matter of a הלכה? halacha?
That seems like a good thing. דתניא, detanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, Braisa, רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yose omer, כל האומר אין לו
תורה, kol ha'omer ein lo Torah, anybody that says I have nothing
to do with תורה, Torah, אין לו תורה, ein lo Torah, doesn't
get any reward from תורה. Torah. So anyways, משמע פשיטא, mashma pshita,
of course! You're not interested in תורה, Torah, you're not getting a
reward. No, אלא כל האומר אין לו אלא תורה, ela kol ha'omer
ein lo ela Torah,
if you say I'm only interested in learning תורה Torah not in
doing, I'm not interested in הלכה, halacha, I'm not interested in going
out of the בית מדרש Beis Medrash and doing, I'm just interested
in learning the you know, learning דף יומי Daf Yomi all day.
So then, אין לו אלא תורה. ein lo ela Torah. All you
get is שכר תורה, schar Torah, you don't get שכר מצוה. schar
mitzvah. So משמע הכא נמי פשיטא, mashma hacha nami pshita, that's also
obviously all you're doing is learning תורה, Torah, you're not doing anything
else. אלא ela no, here's what it should be saying. אלא דאפילו
תורה אין לו, ela de'afillu Torah ein lo, if all you're doing
is learning תוקע עצמו לדבר הלכה, tokeia atzmo lidvar halacha, you're sticking
yourself in the matter of הלכה, halacha, you're not acting on it,
you're just learning הלכה halacha but you never do anything about it,
then, then you don't even get the reward for learning about it.
Why not? אפילו תורה אין לו. afillu Torah ein lo. מאי טעמא
אמר רב פפא דאמר קרא, mai ta'ama amar Rav Pappa d'amar kra,
because the verse says, ולמדתם ועשיתם, u'lemadetem va'asitem,
learn and do. כל שישנו בעשייה, kol she'yeshno ba'asiyah, if it translates
into doing, ישנו בלמידה, yeshno balamidah, then the learning is of value.
כל שאינו בעשייה, kol she'eino ba'asiyah, if you're not in a world
of doing, אינו בלמידה, eino balamidah, your learning is of no value.
Okay, so that's תוקע עצמו, tokeia atzmo, you're stuck in the בית
מדרש Beis Medrash and you never leave it, that's a bad thing.
ואיבעית אימא, v'ibaiyis eima, and if you want you could say, לעולם
כדאמרינן מעיקרא, le'olam kid'amisu me'ikara, it's like you said initially. כל האומר
אין לו אלא תורה אין לו אלא תורה, kol ha'omer ein lo
ela Torah ein lo ela Torah, if you only are in a
world of תורה Torah and not a world of doing, you only
have תורה. Torah. Well isn't that obvious? Of course you only have
תורה, Torah, you're not doing anything. So משמע mashma no, אלא צריכא
דקא מגמר לאחריני, ela tzricha d'ka migma l'achrini, that
let's say you're, you stay in the בית מדרש Beis Medrash all
day, you give a שיעור, shiur, you teach other people הלכה, halacha,
you teach other people what it means to go out and do
מצוות, mitzvos, ואזלי ועבדי, v'azli v'avdi, and they go out and do
מצוות. mitzvos. So you're saying, okay look, I'm staying in the בית
מדרש Beis Medrash but I'm encouraging other people to do מצוות, mitzvos,
I should get rewarded for that. מהו דתימא, ma d'seima, you might
think, אית ליה אגרא לדידיה, is leih agra l'didei, you get reward
for encouraging other people to do מצוות, mitzvos, קא משמע לן, kama'shmalan,
that you don't. If for you, you never leave the בית מדרש,
Beis Medrash, you don't even get credit for other people's מצוות, mitzvos,
you get credit for your תורה, Torah, but if you don't, if
you're like, you know you, you talk a good game but you
never actually translate it into a world of doing, you don't get
credit for other people's doing either. Okay, ואיבעית אימא, v'ibaiyis eima, if
you want you could say, almost done here, תוקע עצמו לדבר הלכה
tokeia atzmo lidvar halacha בדיינא, b'dayana,
it's talking about a judge, דאתי דינא לקמיה, d'asi dina lekamei, a
judge comes to him, וגמר הלכה, v'gemar halacha, he learned the הלכה,
halacha, and it's not really relevant, but it's somewhat analogous, ומדמי מילתא
למילתא, u'medami milsa l'milsa, and he says, oh wait I, I learned
something once that's a little bit relevant, that's a little bit related,
and therefore he applies it. ואית ליה רבה, v'is leih rabba, and
he has a רבי, rebbe, ולא אזיל משאיל, v'lo azil mashi'ul, and
he doesn't ask his רבי, rebbe, okay, what the הלכה halacha is.
So תוקע עצמו לדבר הלכה tokeia atzmo lidvar halacha means you're stuck
on the one thing you learned and that's the one thing you
apply but you don't have enough breadth to apply the right thing.
You ever hear the phrase if all, the only tool you have
is a hammer, every, every problem is a nail? That's the problem.
Okay, and you can ask your רבי, rebbe, and you don't ask
your רבי. rebbe. That's a very bad thing. Okay, דאמר רבי שמואל
בר נחמני אמר רב יונתן, d'amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rav
Yonasan, לעולם יראה דיין עצמו כאילו חרב מונחת לו בין ירכותיו, le'olam
yehei dayan atzmo ke'illu cherev munachas lo bein yarcheisov, a judge should
see himself like a sword is between his thighs, וגיהנום פתוחה לו
מתחתיו, v'Gehenom pesucha lo mitachtov, and גיהנום Gehenom is open underneath him,
the weight of coming up with the right judgment and you have
to have a real יראת שמים, yiras shamayim, שנאמר הנה מטתו של
שלמה ששים גבורים סביב לה מגבורי ישראל, shenemar hinei mitaso shel Shlomo
shishim gibborim saviv lah migibborei Yisrael, מפחד בלילות, mipachad baleilos, fear of
evenings, מפחד של גיהנום שדומה ללילה. mipachad shel Gehenom shedomeh l'layla.
Okay
and therefore if you are stuck on a דבר הלכה dvar halacha
and not really don't have the breath and whatever, that is a
very bad thing. Okay, thank you for staying later and now we
are not only done with that סוגיא sugya but more or less
caught up.
Too bad we had to rush through the really fun part. Oh,
now guess what got out of us, let's just zip through.